Continuing our quest for solid error handling,
whereas a try statement attempts to run code,
the except statement runs code if the code being
run in the try statement causes a runtime error.
Continuing from the previous video, I have
added, to this 522-except file, which shows
a list of figuratives for a language, an except
block on lines 5 and 6. Within the except block,
we see a print statement telling the person
running this app to try again by entering a
number for a figurative. We did not try to run
the code in the previous video because a try
block will not run without an except block, as we
have now, or a finally block, which we will see
in an upcoming topic. I will run this code and
enter a legitimate value. There was no output,
as we will add the code for that in the next
video, but there was no error, which is what
we anticipated. I will rerun the code and
enter an illegitimate value, and this time,
we get the error message that says we did not
enter a figurative, so the except block worked.
In other words, this message looks a lot better
than this message. Before we proceed, let's take a
moment to remind ourselves what an exception is in
Python. An exception is an event that disrupts the
normal flow of the program, often due to some kind
of error or exceptional condition. Exceptions are
types of runtime errors, but they can be handled
gracefully using mechanisms like try, except,
finally, and else blocks, allowing the program to
continue or terminate in a controlled way. Again,
the purpose of an except block is to handle an
exception gracefully and control the message
given when a runtime error occurs, perhaps
even to provide instructions on what to do
to avoid the error in the future, as we have
here with instructions in the except block.